<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Chronicon</title>
                <author>Romualdus Salernitanus</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="print_editor">Print edition</resp>
                    <name>Born-digital critical edition. See source description for the collation exemplars</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="ALIM2_3">Born-digital TEI XML digital scholarly edition by</resp>
                    <name key="PM" xml:id="pm">Paolo Monella</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp key="collation">Conversion from Juxta comparison set to TEI-conformant markup</resp>
                    <name>Generated by Juxta Commons, reviewed manually</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>
                <measure quantity="104290" unit="words">Words: 104290</measure>
                <measure quantity="642387" unit="characters_without_spaces">Characters (withous spaces): 642387</measure>
            </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <ref target="http://alim.unisi.it/">ALIM</ref>
                </publisher>
                <date when="2020-02-03">03/02/2020</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright 2006- progetto ALIM</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="a" facs="https://digi.vatlib.it/iiif/MSS_Vat.lat.3973/manifest.json">
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                <settlement>Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana</settlement>
                                <idno>Vat. lat. 3973</idno>
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </witness>
                    <witness xml:id="a2" facs="https://digi.vatlib.it/iiif/MSS_Vat.lat.3973/manifest.json">
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                <settlement>Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana</settlement>
                                <idno>Vat. lat. 3973</idno>
                            </msIdentifier>
                            <ab>This siglum represents a later hand, probably of the XVII century, in this manuscript</ab>
                        </msDesc>
                    </witness>
                    <witness xml:id="o" facs="https://digi.vatlib.it/iiif/MSS_Ott.lat.2940/manifest.json">
                        <msDesc>
                            <msIdentifier>
                                <settlement>Ottobonianus</settlement>
                                <idno>Latinus 2940, 1st fragment, folios 16r-18v</idno>
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
                    </witness>
                    <witness xml:id="g" facs="https://archive.org/details/p1rerumitalicarums07card/">
                        <biblStruct>
                            <monogr>
                                <author>Guarna, Romualdus</author>
                                <title>Romualdi Salernitani Chronicon (A.m. 130-A.C. 1178)</title>
                                <editor>Garufi, Carlo Alberto</editor>
                                <imprint>
                                    <pubPlace>Città di Castello</pubPlace>
                                    <publisher>S. Lapi</publisher>
                                    <date>1914</date>
                                </imprint>
                            </monogr>
                            <series>
                                <title level="s">Rerum italicarum scriptores: Nuova edizione</title>
                                <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
                                <biblScope unit="part">1</biblScope>
                            </series>
                            <note>Garufi's edition was the collation exemplar from the beginning of the text
			    until (and including) paragraph g163.1-163.5.</note>
                        </biblStruct>
                    </witness>
                    <witness xml:id="b">
                        <biblStruct>
                            <monogr>
                                <author>Guarna, Romualdus</author>
                                <title>Romualdo II Guarna, Chronicon</title>
                                <idno type="ISBN">9788883090561</idno>
                                <editor>Bonetti, Cinzia</editor>
                                <imprint>
                                    <pubPlace>Salerno</pubPlace>
                                    <publisher>Avagliano</publisher>
                                    <date>2001</date>
                                </imprint>
                            </monogr>
                            <series>
                                <title level="s">Schola Salernitana. Studi e testi</title>
                                <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
                            </series>
                            <note>Bonetti's edition was the collation exemplar for the collation
			    from (and including) paragraph g163.6-163.7 to the end of the text.
			</note>
                        </biblStruct>
                    </witness>
                </listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Testo codificato nel formato TEI XML, versione P5, per essere incluso fra i testi che compongono il progetto
          ALIM - Archivio della Latinità Italiana del Medioevo.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab type="level">ALIM2_3</ab>
		<ab type="specific">Born-digital scholarly edition.
			See the introduction in the 'front' element for editorial details</ab>
            </editorialDecl>
      	    <editorialDecl xml:id="longversion">
		<ab type="specific">Paragraph including one of the additions
			distinguishing the 'short' from the 'long' version of the work</ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <variantEncoding location="internal" method="parallel-segmentation" />
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="lat">Latino</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="form">Prosa</term>
                    <term type="source">Letteraria</term>
                    <term type="genre">Storiografia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <creation>
                <date when-iso="1001/1100">XII secolo</date>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2020-02" who="PM">Prima edizione nel formato TEI P5 [livello ALIM2_3]</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

<front>

<head>Introduction</head>

<div>
<head>Aim</head>
<p>The present edition aims at improving
the text of the Chronicon by Romualdus Salernitanus
(Romualdus II Guarna) through a new collation of the text
of the print editions by Garufi 1914 and Bonetti 2001
against A and O, the main witnesses of the 'short version' of the work.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>The Chronicon</head>
<p>The Chronicon is a universal history composed by Archbishop of Salerno
	Romualdus II Guarna shortly before his death (1181). For the
	period going from Adam until 1125, Romualdus compiled previous sources,
	possibly working on a previous compilation (see paragraph 'Authenticity' below),
	while for contemporary events his work is a primary source.
	In particular, Romualdus was one of the protagonists of the
	"Peace of Venice" (1177), a treaty between Emperor Frederick I, Pope
	Alexander III and other political entities of the Italian area,
	covered in great detail in the last part of the Chronicon.
	In fact, Romualdus was a leading figure of the delegation sent by King 
	William II of Sicily to the negotiations in Venice.
	</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Structure of the work</head>
<p> The Chronicon initially follows ancient Jewish, Greek and and Roman
	ancient history, then European (continental and Byzantine) events.
	It then includes a digression on the the story of the Lombards and the Franks
	until Louis the Pious, from paragraph g108.24-109.5 i.e. page 108 of Garufi's edition,
	line 24, to par. g159.9-159.25. From this point on, the scope of the narrative
	returns to be wide, continental, but it progressively focusses on Southern
	Italy, until it substantially becomes a chronicle of its Norman conquest and then
	of the Kingdom of Sicily, ending with the detailed account of the Peace of Venice
	(from par. v-b298a of the present edition to the end of the work).</p>
</div>


<div>
<head>Sources</head>

<p>Garufi 1914 (henceforth "Garufi") has a very informative separate apparatus of footnotes
	providing the sources of each passage of the work. Detailed information and critical
	discussion on the sources of Romualdus and his relationship with Norman
	historiography are in Arndt 1966 (running footnotes); Garufi, XXV-XXVIII
	(introduction); Hoffmann 1967, 165-170; Matthew 1981, 243-249; 258-267;
	Zabbia 2002; Zabbia 2004, 380-382 and 392-394;
	Zabbia 2010, 22 and 25-60.
</p>

<list>
	<item>The main source for the first part of the work (the universal history)
		is Bede, <title>De sex aetatibus mundi</title>,
		integrated mostly with
		Eutropius, <title>Breviarium ab urbe condita</title>;
		Orosius, <title>Historia adversum paganos</title>; 
		Paul the Deacon, <title>Historia Romana</title>;
		Jerome's <title>Chronicon</title> and <title>Commentary on Daniel</title>;
		the <title>Liber Pontificalis</title> and
		Bonizo of Sutri (see Matthew 1981, 245 n. 2);
	</item>
	<item>For the digression on Franks and Lombards, the main sources are
		Paul the Deacon, <title>Historia Langobardorum</title>
		with the related <title>Continuatio Casinensis</title>;
		Gregory of Tours, <title>Historia Francorum</title>;
		Einhard, <title>Vita Karoli</title>;
		Aimoin of Fleury and his continuation
		(see Matthew 1981, 245 n. 3);
	</item>
	<item>The question of his sources for the Norman period (roughly after 999)
		is intertwined with the authorship issue, on which see
		next paragraph and the bibliography cited above,
		but a key source for this period are the <title>Annales</title> by
		Lupus Protospatharius.</item>
</list>
</div>

<div>
<head>Authorship: textual evidence</head>
<p>It is not the task of this introduction to examine in depth the question of the
	authorship of the Chronicon. However, I will shortly summarize the issue.
	The attribution of the work to Romualdus Salernitanus is based on two textual
	notes in the handwritten tradition:
<list>
	<item>a sentence in manuscript C (Paris, Bibliothèque Nationale, Latinus 4933),
		not present in the other main manuscripts,
		probably a marginal note that later entered the text:
		"Ab hoc loco adiunctum est huic chronice per Romualdum secundum
		Salernatanum archiepiscopum".
		The note (not included in the text of my edition)
		is in par. g213.1-213.8, precisely in page 213, line 5 of Garufi,
		between "...iuramentum accepit" and "Dux autem Wilhelmus..." (events of year 1125).
		Garufi reports the note in apparatus (see Matthew 1981, 255-256
		and Zabbia 2004, 382, 388 and footnote 5);
	</item>
	<item>
		a second sentence in par. g293.39-294.2: "Hec autem omnia, que prediximus,
		ita gesta fuisse, nulli dubitationis uel incredulitatis scrupulum moueant,
		quia Romoaldus secundus Salernitanus archiepiscopus, qui uidit et interfuit,
		scripsit hec; et sciatis, quia uerum est testimonium eius" (see Mattew 1981, 239-240).
	       	With "hec... omnia, que prediximus", the text refers to the Peace of Venice.
	</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Authorship: hypotheses</head>
<p>For Matthew 1981, the first note only proves that
	the scribe who wrote it believed in Romualdus' authorship, and the second
	that the report of the Peace of Venice was based on the archbishop's,
	possibly written, testimony. Mattews discusses numerous arguments in favor
	of the thesis that the author of the Chronicon is not Romualdus:
	he suggests that around 1126 an anonymous compiler based in the
	Apulian city of Troia wrote a compilation of universal history reporting
	events until 1125 (see Matthew 1981, 239-256);
	later, "a writer from Salerno decided to set down the events of the
	reigns to Roger II and the two Williams in 1177",
	while only the report of the Peace of Venice "is taken from
	the written, eitiwness, and true account of Archbishop Romuald"
	(Matthew 1981, 269-270). Vitolo 2007, 549-551 follows Matthew, and stresses
	the lack of attention to the famous medicine school of Salerno
	(except for a short note in g189.2-189.5).
	Oldoni (2001 and 2004) suggest that the text until year 893 may have been
	written by Romualdus; the section on years 893-1127 shows "una scrittura
	a più mani ove intervengono, con Romualdo, almeno altri due scribi"; 
	years 1127-1173 were entrusted to Romualdus' collaborators; finally,
	only the section after 1173 was "forse [l]'unica parte certamente 
	originale dell'opera sua".
	</p>
<p>Zabbia 2004 confuted Mattew's arguments and suggested
	that Romualdus is the author of the whole work, though he did not
	rule out the possibility, based on the first note mentioned above
	("Ab hoc loco adiunctum est...', par. g213.1-213.8), that
	the archbishop continued a previously existing universal chronicon.
	In his view, the note "Ab hoc loco..." simply suggests that
	"sino al 1125 l'arcivescono avrebbe condotto il suo lavoro sulle fonti;
	dopo quella data – a partire cioè da quando Romualdo aveva all'incirca
	quindici anni – il racconto sarebbe fondato sulla memoria dell'autore"
	(also see Pio 1996, 26 n. 26), though he adds:
	"Tutto ciò non consente di escludere che l'arcivescono potesse disporre
	di una cronaca in cui almeno parte del materiale fosse già organizzata"
	(Zabbia 2004, 389 and 392, where he writes of a "codice miscellaneo").
	In a later essay (Zabbia 2010), the same scholar
	proposed a theory closer to one of Matthew's: that for the period between 999
	(the arrival of Normans to Southern Italy) to 1125, the source of Romualdus
	was a pre-existing short chronicle, written in Salerno within the first
	fourth of the XII century. For Zabbia, this short chronical was the common
	source of Romualdus' Chronicon for this period and of the Chronicon Amalphitanum
	(Zabbia 2010, 25-42), but comparison between the two works shows that
	Romualdus did not copy his source, but integrated it with other information,
	for example regarding the papacy. See Zabbia 2004, 384 and Zabbia 2010, 21-24
	for further bibliography on the authorship issue.
	</p>
<p>Zabbia's arguments on authorship balance out those of Matthew.
	This leaves the question open, at least for the part of the work before
	year 1125. While internal evidence is not conclusive, the two notes
	mentioned above suggest quite clearly that:
<list>
	<item>The final part of the work – the account of the Peace of Venice –
		was almost certainly either written by Romualdus himself,
		or under his supervision (see second note above);</item>
	<item>the section from year 1125 (par. g213.1-213.8) to the Peace of Venice
		was added, 'adiunctum' by Romualdus as well (see first note);</item>
	<item>the section from Adam to year 1125 constituted something that existed
		before Romualdus (see note in g213.1-213.8: "adiunctum est huic chronice").</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>The hypothesis proposed by Zabbia 2010 essay is economic and entirely consistent with
	this evidence. If Romualdus mixed and summarized different sources (directly or
	supervising the work of his collaborators) for the universal history until 999,
	and mostly followed and integrated the short chronicle postulated
	by Zabbia until 1125, then a scribe could reasonably write in the note in
	g213.1-213.8 that only from that point on ("ab hoc loco") Romualdus added up
	new information to the Chronicon.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Manuscripts</head>
<p>The three oldest witnesses of the work are:
<list>
	<item>A: Vaticanus Latinus 3973, of the late XII century, available in
		<ref type="url" target="https://digi.vatlib.it/mss/detail/Vat.lat.3973">
			https://digi.vatlib.it/mss/detail/Vat.lat.3973</ref>;
		III manifest in
		<ref type="IIIF" target="https://digi.vatlib.it/iiif/MSS_Vat.lat.3973/manifest.json">
			https://digi.vatlib.it/iiif/MSS_Vat.lat.3973/manifest.json</ref>;
	</item>
	<item>B: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, Archivio di San Pietro, E 22,
		of the XIV century, available in
		<ref type="url" target="http://digi.vatlib.it/mss/detail/Arch.Cap.S.Pietro.E.22">
			http://digi.vatlib.it/mss/detail/Arch.Cap.S.Pietro.E.22</ref>;
		III manifest in
		<ref type="IIIF" target="https://digi.vatlib.it/iiif/MSS_Arch.Cap.S.Pietro.E.22/manifest.json">
			https://digi.vatlib.it/iiif/MSS_Arch.Cap.S.Pietro.E.22/manifest.json</ref>;
	</item>
	<item>C: Paris, Bibliothèque Nationale, Latinus 4933,
		of the late XII-early XIII century, available in
		<ref type="url" target="https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc63823p">
			https://archivesetmanuscrits.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cc63823p</ref>.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Another important witness is
<list>
	<item>O: a fragment of MS Ottobonianus Latinus 2940,
		(XIV century), folios 16r-18v, available in
		<ref type="url" target="https://digi.vatlib.it/mss/detail/Ott.lat.2940">
			https://digi.vatlib.it/mss/detail/Ott.lat.2940</ref>;
		III manifest in
		<ref type="IIIF" target="https://digi.vatlib.it/iiif/MSS_Ott.lat.2940/manifest.json">
			https://digi.vatlib.it/iiif/MSS_Ott.lat.2940/manifest.json</ref>.
	</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>The importance of O lies in the fact that, as argued by Schwartz 1978, 139 n. 119,
	it might have been copied from a lost MS, older than A.
	Also see Matthews 1981, 250 n. 1; Zabbia 2004, 387, endnotes 26, 27 and 29;
	Zabbia 2006, 62.</p>

<p>The siglum used by Garufi, Schwartz and other scholars for this manuscript
	is 'Aa'. I am modifying it to 'O' for consistency
	with the other sigla (one letter only, not including
	character 'A' already used for Vat. Lat. 3973), thus
	facilitating the processing of XML files.</p>

<p>A detailed description and discussion of the manuscript tradition can be found in
	Garufi, XXXI-XXXVI; Hoffmann 1967, 156-165 (mostly on MS A);
	Matthew 1981, 241-242; Zabbia 2004, 385-388;
	Zabbia 2006 and Zabbia 2010, 24-25</p>

</div>


<div>
<head>Print editions and translations</head>
<p>The two most recent print editions of the Chronicon are Garufi
	(for which see the review in Erdmann 1930) and Bonetti 2001
	(henceforth "Bonetti"). The latter starts with paragraph g163.6-163.7
	and includes and Italian translation.</p>
	
<p>Bonetti uses Garufi as "testo base" and Arndt 1866 as "elemento integrativo"
	(see 'Nota al testo', Bonetti, 56).</p>

<p>Previously, the work had been published by Muratori 1725;
	Del Re 1875 (from g212.1-212.4, with Italian translation);
	Arndt 1866 (from g163.11-164.9).
	Schmale 1986, 308-371 published the Peace of Venice, based
	on Garufi's text, with a German translation.
	Carucci 1996 is an Italian translation of select passages
	of the Chronicon about the Peace of Venice.
	Loud 2012, 250-268 provides an English translation of the
	narrative of years 1125-1154.
	See Garufi, XXVIII-XXXI for previous print editions, and
	http://www.geschichtsquellen.de/werk/4214
	for other translations and general bibliography.</p>

<p>Bibliographical details on the editions by Bonetti and Garufi
	are in the 'sourceDesc' element of this TEI XML file;
	on the other works cited, in the
	bibliography at the end of this introduction.
</p>

</div>

<div>
<head>Paragraph identifiers</head>
<p>Paragraphs ('p' elements in the TEI XML source) have been labelled
with @xml:id attributes based on Garufi. For instance, paragraph
'g163.1-163.5' goes from page 163, line 1 to page 163, line 5 of
the Garufi edition. In some cases, Garufi's paragraphs have been
further broken into smaller 'p' elements to facilitate collation.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Sigla</head>
<p>As noted in the 'sourceDesc' element,
	in the @wit attributes of 'lem' and 'rdg'
	elements I used abbreviations 'g' for Garufi, 'b' for Bonetti,
	'a' for MS A (first hand), 'a2' for the second hand of MS A
	(probably XVII century) and 'o' for the fragment of MS O.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Long and short versions of the work</head>

<p>MSS B and C present a number of textual passages absent in A and O.
	We thus distinguish between a 'long' (MSS B and C)
	and 'short' version of the work (A and O). Those additions
	correspond to the following paragraphs in the present edition:
	g3.7-3.16, g10.n2-10.n5, g30.n1-30.n3, g179.10-179.11, g186.6-186.7, 
	g186.8-186.8, g186.9-186.9, g186.10-186.11, g187.3-187.4, g187.5-187.8, 
	g187.11-187.14, g188.5-188.7, g189.1-189.1, g191.3-191.5, g191.15-192.3, 
	g195.6-195.8, g198.4-198.5, g198.12-198.13, g198.16-198.17, g199.5-199.8, 
	g199.12-199.14, g200.17-200.21, g201.19-201.20, g202.7-202.10, g203.1-203.2, 
	g203.6-203.6, g205.1-205.2, g206.n4-206.n5, g206.13-206.17, g208.1-208.9, 
	g210.23-210.24, g211.15-211.17, g212.5-212.9, g212.10-212.11, g212.12-212.13, 
	g214.12-214.14, g214.14-215.3, g219.3-219.4, g214.n8-215.n14, 
	g215.n14-216.n10, g216.n10-217.n1, g217.n4-217.n10, g218.n16-218.n23, 
	g219.n1-219.n13, g217.n10-218.n16, g234.n1-236.n10, 
	</p>

<p>The 'p' elements including these additions have been marked with attribute
	@decls="#longversion", in this XML file, linking to the relevant
	'editorialDecl'.</p>

<p>Scholars are unanimously convinced that these are later additions to the
	'short' version' (see Garufi, XXXIV; Matthew 1981, 241-243,
	Zabbia 2004, 386-387; Zabbia 2006, 59-61 and Zabbia 2010, 24-25, 27 and 43-49),
	but Garufi himself includes some of them in his text. He therefore considers
	these ones Romualdus' own additions (followed by Palumbo 1978, 76-78),
	and Zabbia 2006, 60 suggests that the first ones
	(g3.7-3.16, g10.n2-10.n5, g30.n1-30.n3) might actually be lacunae in A,
	rather than additions in B and C.
	Zabbia maintains that those additions are generally consistent with the style
	of the whole Chronicon, that they have been written shortly after
	the composition of the whole work (Zabbia 2004, 397: "interventi
	databili a ridosso della stesura"), that it is not impossible
	that Romualdus himself (Zabbia 2006, 60) or "uno dei suoi
	collaboratori (Zabbia 2010, 25) added them to the Chronicon.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Second hand in A</head>
<p>Someone, probably in the XVII century, copied most of the parts missing
	in MS A (the 'long version additions', plus some missing quires or folios)
	into the marginal space of the manuscript, drawing them from MS B
	(see Matthew 1981, 242).
	In addition to the 'long version additions' mentioned in the previous paragraph,
	I transcribed and collated also the following portions of MS A added by the
	second hand and marked their readings with siglum 'a2' in 'app' elements:
	g180.10-180.12, g180.13-180.15, g181.1-181.1, g181.2-181.5, g181.6-181.10,
	g181.10-181.11, g181.12-182.19, g183.1-184.6, g184.7-184.9, g184.10-184.13.
</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Portions of the work included in fragment O</head>
<p>Witness O (i.e. folios 16r-18v of Ottobon. Lat. 2940) has the following paragraphs:
g168.5-168.7, g168.8-169.4, g169.5-170.14, g170.15-170.16, g170.17-171.1, g171.2-171.6, 
71.7-171.8, g171.9-171.14, g172.1-172.9, g172.10-173.11, g173.12-173.13, g173.14-174.7, 
74.8-175.15, g176.1-176.2, g177.1-177.4, g177.5-177.6, g177.7-177.8, g177.9-178.3, 
78.4-178.10, g178.11-178.12, g178.13-179.2, g179.3-179.7, g179.8-179.9, g179.12-179.14, 
79.15-180.10, g180.10-180.12, g181.1-181.1, g181.2-181.5, g181.6-181.10, g181.10-181.11, 
81.12-182.19, g183.1-184.6, g184.7-184.9, g184.10-184.13, g184.13-185.7, g185.8-186.5,
g186.12-187.2, g187.9-187.11 and g187.14-188.1.</p>
</div>


<div>
<head>Paragraphs missing in A and O (no variants)</head>

<p>Some paragraphs are missing both in MS A (first or second hand) and in MS O.
	For them I am simply reporting the text of Garufi or Bonetti (i.e. Garufi/Arndt),
	without any 'app' elements. These paragraphs are:
	g74.21-74.21, g85.20-85.30, g85.31-86.12, g86.13-86.25, g86.26-87.29, g87.30-88.28, 
	.29-90.15, g90.16-90.20, g90.21-92.5, g92.6-92.7, g92.8-92.9, g179.10-179.11, 
	6.10-186.11, g187.3-187.4, g199.13-199.15, g206.n4-206.n5, g215.n14-216.n10.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Collation exemplars</head>

<p>Garufi was the collation exemplar for the first part of the work,
	from the incipit through paragraph g163.1-163.5. 
</p>

<p>Bonetti was the collation exemplar for the part of the text
	it includes, i.e. from paragraph g163.6-163.7 to the end of the text.
	The legibility of the print in Bonetti's edition is better
	than in Garufi's, so it lends itself to less error-prone OCR:
	this is the reason why I decided to use Bonetti
	as collation exemplar for this part of the work.</p>

<p>In the part of the text collated against Bonetti
	(g163.1-163.5 to the end), whenever I chose the reading of a MS against
	that of Bonetti, and the text of Garufi diverged from that fo Bonetti,
	I recorded both Garufi's and Bonetti's readings in the 'app' element.</p>

</div>


<div>
<head>Parts for collation</head>
<p>I transcribed A and O in TEI XML
using Garufi or Bonetti as noted above,
then performed an automatic collation of the transcriptions using
juxtacommons.org and edited the XML output files file manually.
I divided the text in four parts for collation:
<list>
	<item>for part '1' (incipit to g163.1-163.5), I collated Garufi against A;</item>
	<item>for part '2-alfa' (g163.6-163.7 through g167.4-168.4), Bonetti against A;</item>
	<item>for part '2-bravo' (g168.5-168.7 through g185.8-186.5), I collated Bonetti, A and O;</item>
	<item>for part '2-charlie' (g186.6-186.7 to the end), Bonetti against A.</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Transpositions</head>
<p>In part 2-bravo, the order of the paragraphs
diverges between Garufi, Bonetti and MS A, do to a number of large transpositions
of those paragraphs in the manuscripts.
I chose the order of Bonetti.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>GitHub</head>
<p>The source code of this edition, including transcriptions of the
witnesses and Python software, is in the project GitHub repository
https://github.com/paolomonella/romualdus.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Transcription layers</head>
<p>I transcribed all witnesses
at the 'alphabetic layer', but I provided a sample
'graphematic layer' transcription of the first paragraphs of MSS A, B and C,
available in the edition GitHub repository.
See Monella 2018 (DOI: 10.6092/issn.2532-8816/7286) for a definition of
those layers of representation of the text in primary sources.
For paragraphs from g116.6-118.8 through g163.1-163.5 I only transcribed major variants.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Normalization</head>
<p>The OCR files of print editions
and the transcriptions of manuscripts have been marked
according to module '11 Representation of Primary Sources' of TEI P5.
Provided that quite surprisingly, there are yet no collation tools that compare
XML trees, i.e. that compare TEI transcriptions taking the markup into account,
I had to normalize the TEI transcriptions to prepare them for collation with
juxtacommons.org. I normalized transcriptions through custom Python scripts, which:
<list>
	<item>extracted an 'alphabetic' transcription from those
		paragraphs that had been transcribed 
		he graphematic layer;</item>
	<item>deleted the following tags with their textual content:
		'interp', 'abbr', 'surplus', 'note', 'milestone'.</item>
	<item>normalized numerals, e.g. 'xiiii' from MS A to 'XIV';</item>
	<item>introduced standard text for gaps in the MSS,
		e.g. {Gap in the MS: 1 illegible word};</item>
	<item>chose between 'sic'/'corr', 'reg'/'orig' elements;</item>
	<item>in particular, regularized 'j' to 'i' and 'v' to 'u'
		in all print and handwritten sources;</item>
	<item>capitalized proper nouns and words at the beginning
		of sentences also for MS text
		(e.g. 'pompeius' from MS A to 'Pompeius');</item>
	<item>stripped the markup for the following TEI tags
		(keeping their textual content, if any):
		'rs', 'hi', 'w', 'choice', 'orig', 'reg', 'num',
		'subst', 'add', 'del', 'expan', 'sic', 'seg',
		'lb', 'pb', 'quote', 'title', 'said', 'soCalled',
		'surplus', 'supplied', 'gap', 'l';</item>
	<item>replaced XML angle brackets with [square brackets]
		for 'p' start- and end-tags, thus producing an output
		such as [p xml:id="g3.2-3.6"]: another script then
		restored the angle brackets in the output
		of the juxtacommons.org collation;</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Variant types and subtypes</head>
<p>I added a @type attribute
to all 'app' elements, and a @subtype attribute to some.
Custom Python scripts proposed the values of those attributes,
then I reviewed them all manually.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>List of variant types</head>
<p>Attribute @type
of 'app' can take one of the following values:
<list>
	<item>'substantive'</item>
	<item>'orthographic'</item>
	<item>'punctuation'</item>
	<item>'gap-in-ms'</item>
	<item>'illegible-in-ms'</item>
	<item>'transposition'</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Variant subtypes</head>
<p>In combination with each @type,
@subtype can take one of the following values:
<list>
	<item>In combination with @type='substantive',
		@subtype (if present) can be:
		'missing-in-print', 'num-num', 'missing-in-ms',
		'transposition', 'fs';</item>
	<item>In combination with @type='orthographic':
		'y' (e.g. martirio/martyrio), 'v', 'j', 'ae',
		'h' (e.g. hodie/odie), 'n-pn', 'hi-y',
		'num-word' (e.g. III/tria), 'case',
		'tc' (e.g. iustitia/iusticia),
		'double' (e.g.  successit/succesit),
		'ph', 'cq', 'mpn', 'tz', 'cz', 'ck',
		'word-segmentation', 'ch', 
		', 'dm-mm', 'mn', 'ncx';</item>
	<item>In combination with @type="punctuation":
		"change-punctuation", "add-punctuation",
		"remove-punctuation".</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Variants for which many subtypes apply</head>
<p>For some variants
(i.e. for some 'app' elements), it is impossible
to determine one subtype, either because two subtypes apply
(e.g., for Symmachus/Simachus 'y' and 'double')
or because there are three readings with different types and/or subtypes
(e.g.  Pisa, Bonetti / Pysas, MS A / Pisas, MS O: Pisa/Pysas is 
ubstantive' variant, but Pysas/Pisas is an 'orthographic'/'y' variant).
I took a pragmatic (and certainly debatable) approach to this issue,
as I chose what I thought was the most relevant type/subtype:
for example, I chose subtype 'y' for Symmachus/Simachus
and type 'substantive' for Pisa/Pysas/Pisas.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Distinction between substantive and orthographic</head>
<p>Also, the line
between 'substantive' and 'orthographic' variants is thin.
This is particularly evident for proper nouns, for which the change of one
letter can be considered meaningful. This is why for proper nouns I tended
to choose @type='substantive', except for the most common orthographic
subtypes, such as 'double' (Callixtus/Calixtus), 'y' (Babyloniam/Babiloniam)
or 'h' (Hieronymo/Ieronimo).</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Case variants</head>
<p>Some 'app' elements mark a distinction between
the lowercase and capitalized spelling of the same word:
these elements have @type="orthographic" with @subtype="case".
For example, 'Cainan' (my lemma) vs cainan (reading of Garufi and of MS A).
MSS will always have the lowercase spelling by convention,
because capitalization does not have graphematic value in them.
Those 'app' elements mean that I capitalize a word that was in lowercase
in the print edition, or vice versa.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Punctuation variants</head>
<p>The case of punctuation is similar to the preceding one.
I chose not to transcribe the MSS punctuation, so all 'app'
elements with type="punctuation" mean that I am modifying
the punctuation of the print edition (of the collation exemplar
for that part of the text). For example, I deleted all
quotation marks from the Bonetti edition, but sometimes
punctuation modification implies significant differences
in phrase and sentence segmentation, therefore in syntax
and text interpretation.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Orthography variants</head>
<p>In orthographic variants
(i.e. 'app' elements with type="orthography), I generally tended
not to modify the print edition spelling. I did modify it,
mostly by adopting MS A's spelling, in cases in which 
<list>
	<item>the print edition has an evident typo, which the MS
		does not have (e.g. 'eorem' Garufi / 'eorum MS A
		in g26.12-26.23);</item>
	<item>the MS's form clearly is more standard both in classical 
		dieval Latin and, most of all, more adherent
		to the usus scribendi of the rest of the work
		(e.g. 'espers' in Garufi / 'expers' in A,
		or omicidia G / homicidia A);</item>
	<item>the print edition has a classical diphthong ('ae' or 'oe')
		while the MS has the monophthongized spelling, which
		I preferred, since monophthongized forms are standard
		in the text. For example, in g70.1-70.19 I chose
		A's 'Rome' over Garufi's 'Romae'. This is a sub-case
		of the previous principle, and in 'ae'/'e' variants
		it is marked with @subtype='ae';</item>
	<item>I eliminated a dash distinguishing a composed word
		in the print edition (e.g. in g80.1-80.4 I chose spelling
		'Primiscrinium' over 'Primi-scrinium' of Garufi).</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Factual variants</head>

<p>The aim of this edition is
	to publish a text as close as possible
	to what has been written by Romualdus or his collaborators,
	not to what has actually happened in history, so I did not
	correct fact, names or dates. Besides, such a task would have
	required a historic competence that is beyond my skills.
	The footnotes in the Garufi edition and the essays cited
	in this introduction provide rich critical discussions
	on this matter.</p>

<p>Dates in particular are an aspect in which the Chronicon is often
	imprecise and there is great variability among the witnesses:
	when dates in A or O diverged from those in Garufi and Bonetti,
	I systematically adhered to the print editions.</p>
</div>


<div n="statistics">


</div>


<div>
<head>The text before and after the author</head>

<p>In some passages Romualdus follows a source very closely, but skips
	some words. Garufi sometimes integrates the missing words.
	For instance, in g100.6-103.2 the Chronicon
	copies Paul the Deacon Hist. 14.116 "adest Geisericus
	cum ualidissimo suae gentis exercitu", but skips the words
	"suae gentis", which are found in no MS of the Chronicon.
	In these cases I reject Garufi's integrations based on
	the principle of considering the Chronicon an autonomous text,
	rather than a copy of his sources.</p>

<p>These cases, together with comples philological issues such as
	the attitions differentiating the 'long' and 'short' version
	of the Chronicon, raise interesting, very general questions on
	the work of the philologist.
	Paul the Deacon's text is 'before' Romualdus and his
	(possible) collaborators, while that of the additions may
	be 'after' him (or them).
       	Where is the 'original text' that the philologist approximates?</p>

<p>The 'original text', especially in cases of a complex editorial
	work such as the Chronicon, looks as elusive as the elusive notion of
	'present', at the sliding edge between past and future.</p>

<p>These issues become more evident to us as we get closer to the author.
	Mordenti 2001, par. 9.1 discusses the extreme case
	of transcription and raises "[la] domanda fondamentale della filologia
	[...] quella che riguarda il concetto di testo e, in particolare,
	di testo originale" and quotes D'Arco Silvio Avalle and Cesare Segre:
	"Il concetto di originale, nel senso di testo autentico esprimente
	la volontà dell'autore, è uno dei più sfuggenti ed ambigui della
	critica del testo. [...] le singole opere di uno scrittore costituiscono
	a rigore una sezione a volte casuale e provvisoria – e non sempre
	operata dall'autore stesso [...] di quel flusso continuo di adattamenti
	e di spostamenti successivi attraverso cui si esprimono le tendenze
	fondamentali di un sistema letterario" (Avalle 1972, 32-33); and
	"Ogni testo scritto è in realtà trascritto: da un copista, da un tipografo.
	Anche l'autografo è una trascrizione (dalla brutta copia); e la brutta copia
	costituisce di norma un testo non definitivo. Insomma, ogni trascrizione è
	anteriore o posteriore al testo; nessun testo può essere identificato col Testo"
	Segre 1979, 36.</p>
</div>


<listBibl>

<head>Works cited in the introduction</head>

</listBibl>

</front>

<body>

</body>

</text>
</TEI>
